[Music]
Stanford
University uh harmonic oscillator Let's
uh just very briefly review the harmonic
oscillator because it's going to come up
time and time again in what uh what
happens from here on in as I said
harmonic oscillators are ubiquitous they
are C all over the place anytime you
have a system which has an equilibrium
state it could be classical or it could
be quantum mechanical but uh but
classical in particular if it has an
equilibrium State and you displace it
from equilibrium generally speaking it
will
oscillate it may oscillate with more
than one frequency for example a violin
string can oscillate in the fundamental
uh frequency it can in the first
harmonic the second harmonic and if you
pluck it in odd ways you can make uh
some nasty noises as I'm sure art
knows uh done it many times done it many
times the nastiness because of U
multiple overtones uh clashing with each
other well that's that's probably not
quite right but uh uh but you know what
I mean all right but nevertheless the
oscillations of a violin string are a
collection of oscillators of different
frequency
um but more important to
us are are the oscillators which
comprise the oscillations of the
electromagnetic field and other fields
we're going to come to that and we're
going to do a little bit of quantum
electrodynamics just a little bit but
basically if you have radiation for
example in a uh in a cavity or in a wave
guide or something like that then the
radiation the electric and magnetic
fields oscillate with definite
frequencies again what would be the
equal equilibrium configuration of the
radiation field I said start with
something which has an equilibrium
configuration what is the equilibrium
configuration of the electromagnetic
field the answer is no electromagnetic
field the vacuum empty space with no
electromagnetic oscillations in it no
electromagnetic oscillations in other
words just a empty space with no
electric magnetic fields is the
equilibrium position of the electric and
magnetic fields if you like if you give
the system a knock by for example um uh
sending in some microwaves or something
the system will start to oscillate and
like the like the um violin string it
can oscillate in all of its various
frequencies and those
oscillations um
are called photons or that's not quite
right the oscillations are described or
describe collections of photons and
we'll come to that but not
tonight okay so harmonic oscillators are
terribly important in many ways
incidentally sound waves are also
oscillations a sound wave moving through
a crystal is a again a collection of
oscillations you can think of it wrongly
as each CST cryst oscillating
independently of every other OS Crystal
sorry each atom oscillating
independently of every other atom but
that's not really the way it works each
atom exerts a force on the other atom
and so when you displace one it gives a
knock to the next one and waves go
through the crystal the waves again are
described by harmonic
oscillators and the Quant of the
oscillations are not called photons
they're called phonons for example so
these are things we're going to study
but uh to prepare ourselves for that we
studied a bit the harmonic oscillator
and I want to expand on it a bit remind
you what the rules
are we started with the harmonic
oscillator with a hamiltonian which I
wrote as p^2 over twice the mass and I
set the mass equal to one just uh to
make my life simple you can go back and
do it with a mass not equal to one I
believe in our uh in our book art we do
it with a general mass or we do it with
yeah okay so it's done with a general
mass and then plus Omega squar that's
the spring constant but it also happens
that Omega is the frequency of the
oscillator x^2 /
2 and we constructed creation and
Annihilation operators A+ or
minus which happen to have been momentum
plus I Omega
X now notice not finished yet but notice
if I classically if I were to take this
is plus or minus if I were to take the
two operators a plus and a minus and
multiply them together and then divide
by two I would construct the hamiltonian
all right so we'll come back to that a
minute but in order to be consistent
with uh the notations that are ancient
we'll put a square root of two Omega
here and those are the a pluses or minus
and if you work out classically or
Quantum mechanically the hamiltonian in
terms of a plus or minus here's what you
find oh one more one more quantity one
more quantity is called
n n is equal to A+ a minus as simple as
that and the last time we proved that
the spectrum of igen values of n were
just the integers starting at
zero we showed that A+ and minus were
create were raising and lowering
operators which raised and lowered the
igen values of
n all right so this is a operator whose
igen values are 1 Zer start start with
zero no negative 1es 0 1 1 two 3 dot dot
dot and finally not finally but
moreover the
hamiltonian is equal to
Omega now um I have left out har bar I'm
going to leave it out but then I'm just
going to show you where it goes if we
leave out H the hamiltonian is just
Omega
time
n now where does that come from if you
multiply A+ * a minus clearly you get
something which looks like
this there's a two downstairs that's
this two and there's an Omega downstairs
that's why I have to compensate it with
an Omega here Omega in but Quantum
mechanically there's a little correction
and the correction comes because the PS
because the A+ and a minus don't commute
and that gave us an n +
1/2 the 1/2 is called the ground state
energy or the VAC well if it was a field
Theory we would call it the vacuum
energy if it is a um simple harmonic
oscillator we call it either the Zero
Point Energy or the ground state
energy and it's really a consequence of
the uncertainty principle that you can't
have both p and X simultaneously being
zero and since the hamiltonian involves
p + X2 there's no way they can cancel
each other so there's always going to be
a residual bit of ground state energy
there you don't lose very much if you
just cross it out and forget it because
an additive constant in the energy of a
system really doesn't um change its
equations of
motion so you can ignore it but it is
there uh if uh for some purposes all
right what I wanted to do was to show
you is there anything else yeah there's
one other one other important point that
equation that went into showing that the
A+ and a minuses were raising and
lowering operators it was the
commutation relations of the A+ and a
minus they ax rule when ever you see two
things commute
them right
sometimes of course you get garbage but
uh the Comm the commutators are a minus
with
A+ just equal to
one had I not put the square roots of
two omegas down there the commutator
would have been something a little
Messier and so really the reason for
dividing by square of 2 Omega here was
to get rid of anything on the right hand
side to divide it away this commutation
relation
together with the definition of
n tells you that n is quantized in
integers and the connection with the
hamiltonian is such that the hamiltonian
or the energy levels are
these yeah um last time you didn't
really explain why it went down to state
zero and you said yeah why it stops at
zero no y z is included oh y z is
included okay we're going to
okay what we're going to do is we're
going to demonstrate explicitly what the
ground state is that there is a ground
state and we'll find the ground state by
actually solving the Schrodinger
equation and we'll see that there
definitely is a state with zero
so um what is a wave function a wave
function in this context let's just uh
let's just put parallel to this very
tricky and clever operator structure
here let's write down the wave function
description of the same thing State
vectors are replaced by wave functions
which are functions of
position if we're talking about energy
igen states we could label the wave
functions with a little n down here
indicating which integer they correspond
to the ground state for example will be
i0
well the first excited state would be S
1 and so
forth so State vectors become wave
functions
operators X the operator
X becomes just
multiplication by the coordinate
X I'm trying I'm trying to remember to
use capital letters for operators and
lowercase letters for um for just
numbers
lowercase okay the
momentum is replaced by minus i d by
just derivative with respect to
X again there's an H bar in there if you
want to keep track of har bars oh if you
do want to keep track of H bars here's
where it goes right
here and that's the only place that's
the only place where you have to um
modify what I've done here yeah I guess
maybe
also here we want to put an H bar
downstairs here I
think but um and you can always figure
out where the H bars go by using
dimensional
analysis using dimensional analysis and
remembering the units of har bar will
tell you uniquely where to put the h
bars okay so there's
momentum and uh let's check and see if
there is a solution of the equation a
minus on S is equal to zero in other
words is there a
state you know I can answer your
question faster without let me let me
let me answer your question quickly
without uh and then come back to
calculating um we know that there has to
be a state which is the bottom State we
can't keep going down and down and down
for the simple reason that the
hamiltonian is positive it's p^2 + x^2
p^2 plus Omega 2 x^2 an operator like
that has no negative igen values just as
classically it's either positive or zero
Quantum mechanically it also can't be
negative
and so there's got to be a bottom
there's got to be a floor to the Tower
of uh of energy
levels okay how can we have a floor the
only way we can have a
floor is
if the bottom State let's call it o
let's call it ground
state is
annihilated by the annihilated means
that you get zero when you hit it with a
minus if you didn't get zero whatever
you got on the right hand side would be
a state of one unit lower energy there
is no state with one unit lower energy
the only way for that to happen is for
this to just give zero now once we
know that a minus on o gives zero then
we can look at n so let's look at n now
what does n
do when it hits the bottom State well
well it is by definition A+ a
minus on o but we already know that a
minus on o give zero so this is
zero it's an igen Vector of n with zero
igen value so there must be an IG the
bottom state has to have zero value of
n okay that's an abstract argument but
yeah so if uh Z is an i Vector of n
shouldn't there be an i Vector of zero
on the far right hand side
sorry it's
o wait wait wait this zero here this
state and this are two different
things right that's the igen vector
that's the igen vector and it's
normalized to one and it's not zero in
any sense it's just that its name is
zero you know if I called if I called my
friend art here zero that wouldn't mean
art wasn't here or didn't exist it would
just mean I'm you know being unpleasant
I'm calling him zero you can write the K
over there if you want yeah you can
write you can write zero as a cat but
you have to understand it's not this
zero no but it's it's zero Z so zero
times that answ right question Z zero
times anything is zero so you can write
fact is that it's a vector on the left
hand and right hand side so you can go
put the vector in there and it's just
the zero Vector thank you yeah yeah but
you must not call it this Vector
whatever name you give it you got to
give it some and the the tradition is
just not to write it as a vector but
just to call it zero
yeah uh in the abstract theory of vector
spaces you introduce a vector called
zero and it's sort of special it's the
only one that doesn't have a a catch
sign but as you say it is just another
Vector a rather special one
yeah okay all right so the bottom of the
tower the bottom of the um the bottom of
the energy Spectrum has to be energy H
bar Omega * 12 with n equal to Zer Big N
equal to Zer also little n but let's see
if we can see how far we can go in
calculating all of the wave functions
can we calculate the wave functions
themselves now you might ask I can write
a Schrodinger I can write a Schrodinger
equation I just use for p in the top
equation I use for t d by DX for a Time
independent shinger equation the right
hand side is just the energy igen value
times
s question is it really true that you
can only solve that equation in fact we
could write write down the equation
let's write down the
equation just time independent here it
is time independent roing or equation
it's minus d by dx^ 2
ordinary
derivative minus 12 the 1/2 is the half
in front of the hamiltonian there uh p^2
is DC by dx^
2 s of
X plus the potential energy plus Omega 2
x^2 * s of
X and if this is the time independent
shorting your equation then what I want
to do is to solve the equation that this
is equal to let's call it e for the igen
value for energy Time s of
X that's the same as writing P ^2+ Omega
2 x^2 on a vector is equal to e times
that Vector okay now if you know
anything about differential equations
you'll know this is a uh second order
differential
equation you can always solve it for any
value of the energy here
okay but what will happen for most
values of the energy is the wave
function will not go to zero at infinity
even worse it will exponentially explode
and get big it won't be normalizable it
will not have a finite probability under
it there's no way to normalize it if you
try to normalize it it'll just be zero
because you'll you know the the integral
under the square of the wave function
will be infinite to get rid of that
Infinity you'll have to divide the
you'll have to divide by it and the wave
function will just be zero
everywhere
so the rule is one more Rule and we've
talked about this you know last quarter
3/4 ago or whatever it was is that what
you mean by an honest Vector here is one
whose square integral whose integ the
square of which is square integrable
inte integral s star
s equal
1 okay there were some exceptions to
this for a particle moving on an
infinite line sometimes we introduce
momentum States and position states
which are a little weird in this way
but uh we would like the total
probability to be finite certainly not
exponentially exploding so this is
one additional restriction and it's when
the wave functions are restricted in
this manner when they really form an
honest and good Vector
space then that's when the rest of this
applies
here it only applies if we're interested
in the Square integrable wave functions
which we
are and so the point is that when we
write when we write down the um the
Schrodinger equation there are certain
definite values of energy which will
have square integrable wave functions
those are the true honest igen
functions
uh if the wave function blows up and
goes to Infinity we just throw them away
we say they're not in the
space okay let's see if we can find sin
not the ground state wave
function we could write the original
Schrodinger equation for it
but we can be smarter than that instead
of writing h on S equals e let's write a
smarter equation a simpler equation
let's use the fact that we
know that the annihilation operator
lowering operator excuse me the lowering
operator on the ground state I don't
need to call this s not just
not gives
zero okay what is a minus a
minus I just want to get my signs
[Applause]
right A minus is proportional to pus I
Omega
X now there's some factors in the
denominator there but we don't care
about them because we're just going to
write that this * s of x =
0 and numerical factors like square
roots of Omega they don't matter in this
equation just multiply through by them
and now remember what p is p is minus i
d by
DX - i d by
DX - I Omega x * I of x = 0 now we have
a much simpler equation than we had
before it doesn't even have any second
derivatives in it it only has first
derivatives in it
so we can try to solve
it um the trick for solving an equation
of motion like
this anybody know what the trick
is there there's only a finite number of
tricks in solving differential equations
there's a handful of Tricks SE what's
that separation of variables no there's
only one variable what are you going to
separate
that's
right okay one very standard trick for
linear equations like this is to write
the um is to write the wave function as
the exponential of something
else now this is just a matter of
experience I can't tell you how to uh
how to guess that yeah you can guess it
because when you multiply through by DX
you get X DX so the equation comes out
as a derivative over a over a you
know you know right but it's a the form
L yeah exactly all right so this happens
to be the kind of equation that you
solve you can solve it in many ways but
the one way of solving it is just to
write s of
X is equal to e to some f ofx and try to
figure out what f ofx is all right so
let's try
it um first of all of course we can get
rid of the eyes here I and I factor
out furthermore more we can get rid of
the minus sign CU both of them have
minus signs and now what's the
derivative of s of x to calculate the
derivative of s of
X we simply differentiate and we find
that let's call it S Prime which means
the derivative is equal to F Prime
that's the derivative of f time e to the
F
ofx to differentiate an exponential you
just differentiate the thing that uh in
the argument of the exponential here and
multiply Again by f ofx e to the f e to
the F ofx okay that's S Prime that's
this here and then we add to
that let's we want to add to that plus
Omega x s of
X which means
we're going to add to
this plus Omega x e to the F
ofx now you see what Michael was saying
that the e to the F ofx factors out we
can get rid of
it and that's where the trick that's why
the trick was done in the first
place let's get rid of all this
here and our equation is just D FDX
plus Omega x =
z that's it equals
zero the
FDX came from here plus Omega X they
both multiplied s so we got rid of
s and that's our equation all right this
is really easy to solve
a function whose derivative is a linear
thing what kind of function is
that a quadratic thing so the solution
is quite clearly going to be
proportional to X2 and fact it's going
to be
f of
x is equal to 12 Omega
x^2 plus a constant let's let's put the
constant in there let's put the constant
in there and that's
all H minus minus minus thank
you- 12 Omega
x^2 that tells us that s of
X is equal to e to - 12 Omega x^2 what
about the
constant well we can add it in but that
just puts a numerical constant in front
of the exponential since I haven't
bothered worrying too much about
normalizing it I'm not going to bother
with the constant numerical constant out
in front is
there uh it's got an omea got a one/
square root of Omega in it but it's uh
not terribly interesting for our
purposes this is sin
not of X and notice that it goes to zero
very very fast with x e to the minus x^2
it's a
gaussian it's a
bell-shaped
curve that goes to zero as e to the
minus 12 Omega X2 and is very very
Square integrable I mean if you if we
Square it and integrated it it's
extremely
convergent and so we've succeeded in
finding now we could go back and check
that the original Schrodinger equation
is
satisfied in other words we could plug
this wave function into the shrodinger
hamiltonian up above and calculate what
the energy igen value is but we already
know what it is it's going to be Omega *
12 we know that from all the algebraic
tricks over here so if we stuck this
function back into the Schrodinger on
into this Schrodinger equation we would
discover that e is equal to 1/2 just by
putting it in plugging it in and doing
it so we know the ground state wave
function we have one igen vector of the
energy we see what its physical
properties are it's concentrated near
the origin it's very smooth because a
gaussian function is very
smooth it's concentrated near the origin
it does what you might expect a ground
state wave function of a harmonic
oscillator to do it just sits at the
origin sits very close to the origin or
at least by close now I mean that it's
concentrated near the
origin and um yeah it's the ground state
what about the first excited state I'll
do the first excited state for you it's
very it's almost trivial and then you
can go home and have a lot of fun
calculating the next 50
states it's uh
sort of mindless um fun but how do you
do
it it's how you do it that's more
interesting than what you get well I
know they're both interesting but you do
it by saying look I know what the first
excited state is
abstractly abstractly the first excited
state is equal to
A+ times the ground state I know what
the ground state is and I know what A+
is so let's just apply A+ to the ground
state here's the ground
state
A+ is p + I Omega X and that will tell
us what the first excited state is all
right so in terms of wave functions S1
of
X is equal or proportional
to p + I Omega
X now p is min - i d by DX
plus I Omega
X
on e to the
minus 12 Omega
x^2 so all we have to do now is to
calculate a derivative but you know I
already did this I already did this we
did it with the opposite sign here we
did it with a minus to get
zero if I do it with the opposite sign
and get zero that means if I do it with
the sign here I'm just going to get
twice the answer that I would
get go back I did this operation on here
and got zero that's the way I solve the
equation right so if this plus this
acting on this gives zero then it must
mean that this term and this term give
the same thing apart from a sign but
once I know that then I know that when
you change the sign of the
uh over
here instead of having them cancel
they'll just double the
answer so this is just going to be
twice I Omega that's not so interesting
it's just a it's just a numerical Factor
happens to be imaginary but who cares
but it has
x * e to - 12 Omega x^
2 so structurally it's different it's
not just the gaussian function it's the
gaussian function times x what does that
look
like that looks like
this again it's very small far away the
fact that there's an X here doesn't make
it big far away because it's totally
overwhelmed by the E to-
x^2 but it has to be minus H it has to
be minus when X is negative yeah good
it's negative yeah well it's twice an
imaginary number times
Omega right uh but whatever it does on
one side it has the opposite sign on the
other
side uh it's an odd function odd meaning
it changes sign when it goes through the
origin right so let's all right so let's
uh let's make it negative on this side
goes down and then comes up zero and
then goes to zero again it's odd meaning
to say that when you reflect it it
changes sign it's it's anti-symmetric
you would say it's
anti-symmetric the probability which is
the square of this is symmetric but
notice that the probability goes to zero
at the
origin if you're in the first excited
state of the harmonic oscillator the
probability that you find the oscillator
at the origin is
zero interesting
fact
uh that's the first excited
state it has the ground state had no
nodes a node means that the wave
function is zero somewhere the ground
state had no nodes the first excited
state has one node
each time you act with
A+ you can you can just spend a little
bit of time with it you'll see how it
works each time you act with A+ you make
a higher order polom in front of e to
minus Omega each time you hit it with
another
A+ it'll give you X
SAR X S Plus another term X cubed after
a
while each time you'll get a higher and
higher order polinomial and each time
you'll add a node so the next wave
function the spin the uh the second
excited
state um
looks has two
nodes the third one has three
nodes and if you work
out the 17th it looks something like
this
each time you act with A+ you wind up
pushing the wave function out more for
example zero the ground state was
concentrated near the near the center
the factor of X here tended to push it
out a little
bit why does it push it out because X is
bigger far away than it is nearby and so
it pushes it out after you've done 17
factors or maybe it's 24 or whatever
you'll find that the wave function is
pushed out near the wings small near the
origin oscillating and then and then
plop goes to
zero either symmetric or
antisymmetric either symmetric or
anti-symmetric and as you go up you get
more and more
Wiggles and the whole thing gets pushed
out further and further what do The
Wiggles mean what's the implication of
The
Wiggles Wiggles mean
momentum okay what's the implication of
it being far away from the
origin potential energy so as you keep
exciting it you create more and more
potential energy by pushing the wave
function out where x s is large but at
the same time you create more and more
momentum as that oscillator swings
through the
origin what's happening is the
oscillator is trying to do what
classical physics tells you what ought
to do that the higher the energy the
more likely it is to be found far away
but it also may be found close and if
it's found close it ought to have a high
momentum so that's why it tends to
oscillate very quickly near the origin
and more slowly far away but uh that's
the basic physics of
it I if I drew it well it should
oscillate more rapidly near the
center and less rapidly far away just
indicating the fact when it swings to
the origin of course it has more
momentum okay that's uh those are the
first two wave functions yes um so it
seems like uh as n becomes very large uh
the correspondence principle does not
hold for the syonic oscillator what
would you say the correspondence
principle is um that when n becomes very
large it looks like a classical it do
well it and in fact what you have to do
to see the classical motion is you have
to take wave packets you have to
superpose many energy
levels for example if you take the
ground state start with the ground
state that's a nice smooth wave packet
Now display it dis place it off to the
side here it's no longer the ground
state in fact it's not even an energy
igen State altogether it does have an
average
energy but now take the time dependent
Schrodinger equation the time dependent
shinger equation has every energy level
oscillate with a different
frequency the result is that this wave
function is not time independent and
what happens it starts to swing back and
forth
it starts to swing back and forth as it
swings near the center it gets lots and
lots of Wiggles but it stays of the same
general
shape Wiggles and then it comes out this
side after a while nice and smooth again
and then it swings back and forth and
back and forth and it looks very much
like a classical oscillator and in fact
the higher the energy the more it looks
like a classical
oscillator uh just because the higher
the energy and the bigger the swing
the smaller the ratio of the uncertainty
to the size of the Swing when the swing
gets very big it sort of dominates the
spatial structure of it okay that's
that's the basic
um physics of the harmonic oscillator
you can work out the second level third
level uh by the time you get to the
fourth level you won't want to see it
anymore but uh but it's
straightforward
um good
question yeah uh on your drawing of the
second level yeah shouldn't shouldn't it
go through zero at
zero
uh it going to be x s is um no I don't
think so I don't think so I think uh I
think there's a constant term also yeah
yeah yeah it's not it's not just x
squared times
yeah right question
hamiltonian you wrote originally the
upper left they already implicitly
contain the normalizability in it so
yeah uh I'll tell you where it's assumed
you you want to know where it's
assumed you want to know where in this
over here it was assumed yeah it's
assumed in in the fact that A+ and a
minus are Herm mission conjugates of
each
other if you were to take a wider class
of wave functions
that were not Square
integrable then A+ and a minus would not
be commission conjugates of each other
that's where it's assumed and I did
assume that uh and um right so
right is there a way in general of
recognizing when a hamiltonian
written yeah if it's a harmonic
oscillator
um and here and there sort of
sporadically and uh this or that uh
sometimes you encounter a a solvable
example and when they're solvable they
can usually be solved by these kind of
tricks but um they're very rare in the
space of
possibilities and um by some fortunate
accident the harmonic oscillator is one
of them and the hydrogen atom or the
idealized hydrogen atom non-relativistic
hydrogen atom with a point nucleus
happens to be one of the solvable
examples
uh
okay now I have in my notes two other
subjects for
tonight um with the idea of uh
discussing atoms a little bit further
but more than atoms discussing
everything that there is about quantum
mechanics and field Theory two things
Spin and boson Fon different the
difference between or what bosons and
ferons are I have uh well I guess I'll
go according to my um to my notes here
I'll follow my notes I have spin first
and then bosons and Fons so let's talk
about half spin the spin of the electron
or the spin of the
proton which happens to be half spin
which means that the spin or the angular
momentum of an electron at rest at rest
that has no orbital angular momentum it
has no R cross
P all it has is spin so spin is a kind
of angular momentum that's attached to a
particle it's your choice whether you
want to think of it as just an abstract
concept or whether you want to think of
it as a tiny little thing which is
literally spinning
spinning about an
axis when I say it has no momentum I
mean to say it has no Center Mass
momentum uh and it's a matter of choice
and taste whether you want to think of
it as literally being a little spin or
just an abstract property that you U
mathematical property that you attach to
the
electron but whatever it is it is
angular momentum it transforms on into
rotation when you
transform when you rotate coordinates
the state transforms now we've already
been through this we spent U most of a
quarter talking about the half spin
system so I'm going to go through it
quickly you should go back and read the
early parts of the
um of the uh previous
lectures we talked about a spin
having two states up or down but then we
said wait a minute if it can be up or
down it can also be left or right but if
it can be left or right it can be in or
out and we worked out the states
describing those things The Operators
which described uh the components of the
spin and I didn't tell you but we were
talking about the angular momentum of a
spinning particle or of a half spin
particle so let's see how we can
understand that now that we've talked
about angular
momentum the thing that characterizes
angular momentum is first of
all that there are three components of
it but just the fact that the three
components of it is not enough it must
be that those three components are
literally associated with the X Y and Z
directions of space you could have them
connected with something else some other
internal Dimensions or whatever but once
you
have matrices once you discover that
your system is being described by
matrices three of them which have the
commutation relations of angular
momentum then they are angular
momentum uh actually there's no choice
about that as long as the three matrices
you're talking about are literally
associated with an X and A Y in a z
direction of space so let me write down
again what the basic commutation
relations of angular momentum
are l i LJ and let's write just LX let's
see um let's take the LZ with the LX LZ
with LX is just equal to I times
ly okay and the other three the other
two are just cyclic
permutations okay you may have noticed
that these commutation relations are
closely related to the commutation
relations of the poy matrices so let's
write the three po matrices and check
whether this is true of the three po
matrices
here they
are Sigma
Z is equal to 1 - 1 0
0 now we've made a choice we've made an
arbitrary Choice we've decided to take
Sigma Z to be the diagonal matrix in
other words we are working in the
representation of the Z component of the
spin we've chosen to take that to be
diagonal and of course the igen values
what are the igen values of this Matrix
the igen values of this Matrix are plus
one and minus one representing up and
down okay then there was Sigma X Sigma X
was 1 1 0 0 and finally Sigma Y is equal
to Min - i i0
0 there are ambiguities in these you can
rotate them and change uh change them
but uh there's
no nothing um important happens there's
no minus in Sigma
x no no minus in Sigma
X all three are
Herm a real Matrix meaning to say it's
if its entries are real numbers if it's
Herm Mission it's
symmetric as the this and this if a
matrix is Herm Mission and imaginary it
must be
anti-symmetric so that's
this okay let's check the commutation
relations let's multiply Sigma Z by
Sigma
X and that's equal to 1 - 1 0
0 0 1 1 1
0 this times this is zero this times
this is one up in here
zero down here minus
one
zero that's not quite Sigma y but it's
almost Sigma y it would be Sigma y I
think um is it I * Sigma y or it's I *
Sigma y
yeah now that's nice but it's not the
commutator the commutator is this
minus Sigma X Sigma
Z that's the
commutator and that has 0 1 1
0 1 0 0- one
and if you go through it you don't get
zero what do you
get exactly the same thing you got over
here equals I Sigma
y so we have not quite what we wanted we
have
instead commutator of Sigma Z with Sigma
X is twice I Sigma
y does this mean these are not angular
momentum or does it mean that we're not
talking about rotations no it just means
we've normalized the sigma matrices
incorrectly let me here's the
trick
take
s and Define it to be Sigma / 2 for each
component for each component take s
being half the poly
Matrix seems a little bit odd but nobody
told us uh what the uh what the angular
momentum was supposed to be so let's
just take it and see what we get then we
get let's uh let's put a two in here a
two in here and that all together
divides by four right I put a two here a
two here I've divided the whole thing by
four two divided by four is one
half so yes half the poly matrices
satisfy exactly what they're supposed to
satisfy SZ with
SX is equal to i s
y and likewise for the other commutation
relations so we see this little system
of 2x two matrices acting on two
component vectors up or down are
actually representing a very primitive
and simple angular momentum system
uh it's a thing which you can think of
as attached to the
particle attached to the particle is a
little Spin and the little spin is
simply described by this system here
okay but now we can answer the question
what are the igen values of let's say
the Z component of the angular momentum
let's go to the Z component of the
angular momentum the Z component of the
angular momentum let's put some twos
here now that we know what we want 1/2
minus a half 12 half 2
2 notice that the igen values of the Z
component of angular momentum are a half
and minus a
half when we were working out angular
momentum I told you and I showed you
that there were two kinds of multiplets
there were the half spin
multiplets let's put zero over
here sorry there were were the integer
spin
multipet where the magnetic quantum
number M
was 0 1 2 3 -1 - 2 -3 and so forth with
the central point being at zero here
being one of the possibilities now
remember the the raising and creation
raising and lowering operators Shift You
by an integer but that doesn't say you
start zero it says you either you start
with zero or you
start at a
half a half minus a half and then 3
halves minus three Hales depending
on the overall angular momentum if it's
been a half then there's only a half and
minus a half
and that's what we have
here we could have guessed all of this
by saying look we seem to have the
mathematical possibility of having half
spin that means there are two states
once we know there are two states we can
say the angular momentum of this one
must be plus a half the angular the Z
component must be plus a half that one
minus a half and we can go and start
building uh the structure structure up
the way we
did uh year and a half ago or year ago
whenever it
was uh well wasn't that was that long
ago I don't remember okay
so every
particle has a spin the spin may be zero
if the spin is zero it's just called a
spin zero
particle the higs boson is a spin zero
particle the dudon is a spin zero
particle
uh yes nuclei can be particles they are
particles they have no angular momentum
in their rest frame on the other hand
some nuclei do have Spin and
uh but some atoms have
spin but the the important thing is um
or we're going to concentrate on is the
half spin particles the
electrons the muon
neutrinos quarks all the ones that
really we think of as
fundamental or some of the ones we think
of fundamental have half
spin okay all of this means that there
are two kinds of angular momentum
orbital angular momentum and this is
true in classical physics 2 orbital
angular momentum is the angular momentum
of the center of mass of a system in the
center of Mass frame if the system is
spinning then it has spin the same is
true here and what is the total angular
momentum the total angular momentum is
the sum of them it's a vector so it's
the vector sum of the two kinds of
angular momentum and it's true here too
so I'll write down the equation but
we're not going to do very much with it
the total angular momentum is called
J again it's a notation I don't know
where it comes from it's again a
vector and it's equal to the orbital
angular momentum L which is R cross P
plus the spin plus
S I just tell you that because you'll
see that all over the place when you're
doing quantum mechanics particularly in
atomic physics you'll see that the total
angular momentum is called
J and it's l plus s for a particle
any questions about
spin I don't want to do too much tonight
so uh we can stay with spin for a while
or um or we can
um I'm just wondering how do you uh like
if you're given some system with the J
how would you identify as for usually
given usually given something different
usually given the knowledge that the
spin is a half for example and that the
orbital angular momentum could be 1 Z if
the orbital angular momentum is zero
then the only angular momentum it has is
the
spin if the orbital angular momentum is
one then we need some rules for what we
get if we add an or an angular momentum
one to an angular momentum of a half
question is what do you get
yet and um I wasn't going to go into
that now the problem of the addition of
angular
momentum it's a straightforward problem
but um we won't do it
tonight be happy to go through it uh
another
night but there are rules mathematical
rules for adding angular momentum of uh
of two systems basically you have two
systems you have the spin system system
and the orbital system or you could just
have two spins or you could have two
different orbital angular momentum
systems uh the the net system has its
own angular momentum and there are rules
quantum mechanical rules for adding them
uh let's not do it
now question yeah um you said we can
think of this
uh
uh not the orbital but the uh the the
spin as being either actually like this
physical thing spinning or we can think
of it in a more theoretical
way um what what is the background for
uh the experimental background or
whatever that that made them introduce
this notion of spin well the first
experimental
background came partly from
spectroscopy and partly more importantly
from uh from the periodic table
so that's where I want to get I want to
get to the periodic table a little bit
and show you how spin comes into
it uh it was poy who realized that uh
that to understand the periodic table
the electron had to have an additional
property okay that brings us to the
issue of fans and bans which is closely
connected to the poly Exclusion
Principle at least in the case of fans
all right let me let me just motivate it
in terms of uh chemistry a little
bit it was one of the motivations the
other came from spectroscopy but
um uh it's it's not as clear it's not as
obvious
the if you remember the um
the angular momentum squared L
squ is equal to l * L + 1 is that what I
want um
yeah and if we look when we looked at
the levels the energy levels of the um
of the hydrogen atom Solutions which we
didn't do but I just told you a fact I
told you a fact that there's some extra
degeneracies each one of these has 2 l+1
States but there were additional
degeneracies I'll I'll redraw them for
you the horizontal axis is L the
vertical axis is energy these are the
energy levels of the hydrogen
atom and down at the bottom is the
ground state of the hydrogen atom with
the lowest energy level of it all and
it's an swave meaning to say it has no
angular momentum no orbital angular
momentum the solutions of the shinger
equation the energy is in fact negative
you start at some negative value Min
-3 point something electron volts but
I'm just putting it here arbitrarily at
the zero is somewh up
here okay so that's the first level
now at the L equals zero there are
states with this is the state with no
nodes in the wave function then there's
one with one node two nodes three nodes
and so forth so there are more States
here I'm just drawing them schematically
completely
schematically okay they're more in fact
they they get closer and closer together
as they get up here near E equals z but
that's not too important for us now we
go to L equals
1 and L equal
1 there's the lowest energy state of L
equals
1 and each L equal 1 state has three
components 2 L + 1 has three
components and the ground state of L
equals 1 has more energy than the ground
state of L equals 0 why because it's got
angular momentum so of course it has
some more energy so it's going to be up
a little bit higher in fact this whole
collection of levels here is going to be
raised up because of the angular
momentum and it's raised up in a rather
surprising and um
I suppose you could say elegant I'm not
sure it's elegant it's uh it's it is
what it is all right so the first the
first lals 1
level occurs at the same place as the
second L equals 0 level it's degenerate
with it so it's three states over
here and then the pattern
continues the next three states are
degenerate with
this and so forth
degenerate means it has the same energy
then you go to L equals 2 I'll use a
different color you go to Lal
2 which is over
here and what you find when you solve
the equations this is supposed to be at
the same level here as you find again
the first L equals 2 state is higher
than the first L equals 1 state but it
happens to occur exactly where the
second L equals two state is is which is
exactly where the third L equal 0 state
is it's a mouthful but you know what I
mean you go up to here and how many
states are there five 1 2 3 4 five 1 2 3
4 5 and so forth and that's the pattern
all right now you count the number of
states now you count the number of
states uh one here at this energy level
whoops yeah one here
four
here zero angular momentum plus angular
momentum one
four 9
here 16 here
evidently uh L squar
levels if you look at the way electrons
fill the shells in idealized very
idealized chemical description of um of
a period IC table where it's up there
but
um uh you see that first of all there
was hydrogen which has one
electron and when you look at Helium
which has two electrons you find out
that uh that uh the it's consistent it's
consistent with an energy which would be
what you would get if you put both
electrons into the ground
state things are a bit different course
instead of having let's go to helium
this is hydrogen let's go now to helium
helium has a nucleus of charge two qal 2
charge two so it pulls on the electrons
tighter the whole structure is rescaled
but that's not important the charge is
bigger that pulls the electrons in
closer but the basic structure is the
same and now you look at Helium you find
out first of all there's a helium ion I
helium ion means one electron instead of
two
electrons okay and you study the helium
ion and the helium ion looks exactly the
same as the
um as the hydrogen with the exception
that you have to plug in twice as much
charge that uh spreads the energy levels
out and rescales them but same
structure so the ion looks like
exactly like the and the ground state of
the helium ground state of the helium
ion looks as if it's one electron in the
ground state of the helium uh wave
function then you put another electron
in okay what do you expect well the
natural expectation would be if you put
another electron in the ground state of
that will be put that electron also in
the lowest energy State why do anything
else if you want to keep the energy as
low as possible put them all into the
ground
state so you try that second electron
into the ground state uh wave function
and it works just fine it gives you the
right rough description of the helium
it's not quite exactly right because
it's ignoring the interaction between
the electrons just pretending the
electrons are just experiencing the
nucleus let's take that as a as a
working uh approximation ignore the
interaction between the electrons put
two electrons into the ground state of
the helium uh wave function and it works
gives you the right energy for the
helium well what happens if you were to
make a helium ion by putting an extra
electron in instead of no instead of uh
the uh the ion with only one electron
incidentally there's also an ion with no
electrons it's just called a deuteron a
um helium nucleus
okay one electron two electron put three
electrons in What's the guess right into
the ground state why anything else but
no that's not what happens what happens
is it goes in to the first excited state
so you put two electrons in the helium
into the ground state and the third one
doesn't want to be there it wants to get
into the next excited state why it could
have saved energy you could have had a
lower energy state in the ground state
if that electron went into the
um went into the ground
state okay so Along Comes poy and says I
have an idea my idea is that no two
electrons can ever get into the same
state something about
electrons is
such I won't call it a repulsion it's
not right to call it a repulsion it's an
exclusion principle when an electron is
in a state you can't fit another one in
somehow the mathematics won't allow but
wait a minute we already said we could
put two electrons into the helium ground
state so it's talking nonsense the PO
Exclusion Principle doesn't work it only
works somehow when you put a third one
in now PO said that's not what's going
on he said really you can't put two
electrons into the same state but an
electron has more properties than just
its orbital motion he said I'm going to
make up a new property and the new
property has to be such that the
electron comes with two values of it two
values of it in that case you can put
the electron one electron into the
ground
state and let's call it the up electron
remember the electron can now have two
properties we're going to call them up
and down we can call them left or right
or we could call them anything we
want uh but let's give them the new
property
uh which uh po eventually realized had
something to do with angular momentum
and said if you can put two electrons in
a state not because you're allowed you
can't put two electrons in a state but
you can put two electrons into the same
orbital angular momentum state if you
give them opposite
spin if one of them is put in in the UP
State and the other one is put in in the
down state then I can save my crazy
exclusion princi
principle I can save my crazy Exclusion
Principle if I assume that the electron
has one more property in addition to its
motion in addition to its orbital motion
that it has a thing which I would call a
spin now in fact there was there were
previous
um reasons to believe in an angular
momentum like that but they're not as
transparent and I won't try to get into
them um that was his basic reasoning
electron has another
property a two valued
property once he knew there was a two-
valued property he was often going he
invented matrices to describe that two-
valued
property and uh before you know it he
had the poy matrices and he understood
the whole thing but um let's go to the
let's go to
the next atom Let's see we go to um
lithium lithium has three
electrons we would naturally expect for
lithium you do the same game now the
nucleus has charge three so it's much
more
attractive charge three you put two
electrons into the ground state that
were for the for the no electron case
the one electron case the two electron
case lithium lithium
ions it works perfectly well to put the
electrons into the ground state not if
there's no electrons but if there's one
or two and indeed you find out that when
you put the third electron in into the
lithium to make it neutral it goes into
the first excited state it goes into the
first excited state meaning the state
with angular momentum
one okay and that works out well it
works out the energy levels of the of
the lithium atom work out reasonably
well that
way what about the ion of lithium
well you've filled up the two lowest
energy states you've only put you have
three states
here you could add oh oh you could add
another electron in any one of these
states let's go back a step let's go let
me go back a step let's forget for a
moment the spin and let's talk about the
um the atoms if there was no spin but if
there was po Exclusion Principle let's
try Po's old idea except without the
spin what would you
find indeed you would find two you would
find one helium in helium you would find
one
electron am I saying this
right in the ground
state but then to keep the energy low
you could put the second electron in any
one of four
states in any one of four
states if you didn't want to double you
didn't want to violate the Exclusion
Principle there would be four distinct
helium
atoms four distinct helium atoms
depending on which state you put the
next electron in that was not right the
helium ground state was unique did not
have uh this
peculiarity what Po's idea was no you
don't go to the second state here and
there are not four possibilities there's
just a helium atom with one electron and
the helium atom with two electrons both
in the ground state now you come to
lithium now you come to lithium you put
the first electron
in forgetting spin where can it
go first electron
here I'm getting tired as usual what I'm
trying to do is explain why there are
eight different can you see this
periodic table up there all right the
second row for has eight entries I
hope has eight entries it has eight
entries how do we understand those eight
entries two * one exra electron we add
an electron yeah yeah we add the first
two electrons and put them in the ground
state
and that uh that's the
um and we're finished with the ground
state right then how many more states do
we have if we only occupy the first
excited state in other words how many
possibility how many different ways can
we make atoms well we can have we can
put an electron in any one of four
states in the first excited state but if
we're allowed to play with a spin then
there's anyone of eight
any one of eight possibilities h 2 six 2
six making mistake P orbitals are six 2
P6
1 there's there's two P orbitals in each
of three spatial directions so there's
two electrons in in each
P there are four states at the first
excited
level six or p and the other two or S1
yeah
okay is the angular momentum zero and
the three angular momentum
one I think that's that's it there's
there's angular momentum zero and three
angular yeah that's the that's the four
but if now you double it by the spin it
becomes
eight yeah you should have a total of
eight not two right that's fine
okay that that's how spin was discovered
that's how spin was discovered and the
fact that it really was angular
momentum that was that could be checked
by putting the atom in a magnetic
field if this if the
electron's additional degree of Freedom
was really angular momentum that would
mean that since the electron is charged
that the electron would be behaving like
a little magnet if it was really Ro
spinning
and it was charged it would behave like
a little uh like a magnet like an
electromagnet current going around in a
loop if that were the case and you put
the electron into a magnetic field
preferentially it would either it would
lie along the magnetic field or opposite
to the magnetic field with two different
energy
levels okay so if you took the hydrogen
atom with one
electron and now you put it in the
magnetic field the two possibilities for
the electron spin along the magnetic
field and opposite to the magnetic field
would now have two different energy
levels so the two states of the hydrogen
atom which previously had been comp the
ground state ground state of the
hydrogen atom with an electron in it the
electron could have been pointing in one
way or the other way they had exactly
the same energy in the first
approximation and now you put it in a
magnetic field and you find that the
energy levels are split and they split
exactly as if the electron were a little
magnet uh because of its angular
momentum so the fact that it had angular
momentum that could be tested by putting
it in a magnetic field the fact that it
had two
levels that was consistent with the uh
with the PO Exclusion Principle and the
fact that um
uh or the assumed fact that you can't
put two electrons into the same state
now this was all all wild guessing it
was wild guessing that you couldn't put
two electrons in the same
state it wasn't quite so wild that it
was angular momentum because that could
be tested
experimentally but
um The Next Step which I think was was
it was it
po it was the one person that it wasn't
was the person that that idea was named
for
Fairy um durak it must have been Dak
again it might have been po it was
either poy or durak
who had the idea that there were two
kinds of
particles particles which satisfied the
POI Exclusion Principle where you
couldn't put two in the same state and
in particles where you could put two in
the same state and not only that it was
preferential to put more than one in the
same
state um it was already known that
photons photons for our purposes now are
just particles it was already known that
a classical wave of photons was simply a
collection of a large number of photons
all in the same state all in the same
Quantum state so it was known that there
were particles that you could put into
the same
state Einstein figured him out and again
it was named after Boza because Einstein
figur it out and
uh uh wasn't Boza although Boza did
some was he in the mix somewhere what's
that enrio fer was he in that same group
no he came later and his contribution
was
different um the Discover of this what
is called the statistics of particles
their their bosen the ban or firon
character was Einstein and po I believe
or it might have been Einstein der and
po I'm not sure uh uh what the actual
history was and
um uh it uh it was not the the other
people although they made major
contributions question I think it was
Einstein who gave gave those are the
credit uh for for the discovery yeah um
when you talk about photons they're SE
they're independent particles but when
we talk about electrons we associate
them with a hydrogen what happens if you
have just a stream of electrons you
can't put two of them in the same
state that's why you can't make a laser
that lasers
electrons a laser creates lots of
photons all in the same Quantum
State uh
you would have a pretty wild thing if
you could get electrons into the same
state and do the same kind of things
with them but you can't you have a
rather remarkable microscope that you
could uh you have electron microscopes
but this would be a rather Superior
electron microscope so the momentum this
L it's not related to rotation around
the nucleus it is of course it is if
there is no nucleus if it's just oh then
it's just R cross P you know a particle
a particle moving in free space just
moving along a line can have an angular
momentum AR cross P relative to some
origin yeah yeah yeah yeah the angular
momentum is relative to an origin that's
because R is relative to an
origin the definition of R is relative
to an origin fixing fixing an
origin you need to and the whole idea of
rotation is about some origin the whole
idea of rotation picks I should have
emphasized that in the beginning
whenever you're talking about angular
momentum whenever you're talking about
rotation you're picking a special point
to study it about now in the case of an
atom it's natural to pick the nucleus to
be the point that you uh the point of
symmetry uh for a particle moving in
free space every point is a point of
symmetry uh rotational symmetry so it's
not it becomes a less interesting uh
thing but for the um for the atom
there's a natural Center to talk about
rotations about we should have
emphasized
that question yeah so why are there two
rows of eight elements and then two rows
of
18 18 is twice
annoying but why are there two I don't
know why at some point the whole picture
breaks down and doesn't make any
sense and and pretty quickly in fact um
the picture of shells and filling
shells is more than a little bit naive
it completely overlooks the interactions
between the electrons now by the time
you have a fairly large atom there's
basically as many electrons in the inner
core as there are protons at the center
so to ignore the interaction of the
outer electrons with the inner electrons
makes no sense at all so I mean the
whole thing breaks down pretty
badly and uh and then and then there's a
zillion rules that I I don't Mis
impression that the the the the more
electrons you have the bigger and the
bigger the atom gets but actually they
don't get that much bigger no they get
they they don't get bigger practically
not at all and the reason is because the
more electrons what happens is very
simple the more protons you have in the
nucleus the larger the charge that tends
to pull in the inner core of the
electrons the inner shells of the
electrons and what's left over if you
have let's say one veence electron is
one veence electron moving in what kind
of field the field that it's moving in
is n protons and N minus1
electrons right so that one extra veence
electron is basically thinks it's a
thinks it's hydrogen and it's no bigger
than hydrogen really it's essentially
almost the same size as
hydrogen so what that's I think that's
what you were saying right atoms do not
get bigger appreciably they get very
slowly bigger but they don't get
appreciably bigger as you add
electrons as you add protons and
electrons at the same time the other
interesting thing that I I ran into is
the with hydrogen atoms the reason that
they stay as far apart from each other
is because of electrical
repulsion hydrogen atoms H oh there's
also an important component from the PO
Exclusion Principle well that's what I
was going to say that's the exception
the rule is for most atoms it's po
repulsion that keeps them
apart
okay where are we yeah so we want to
talk about what bans and fans I guess
this this
might be too much to answer but is the
is the Exclusion Principle a separate
postulate no that time yes okay now it
is not now it's part of basic special
relativity together with quantum
mechanics quantum mechanics without
special
relativity uh it's a postulate but the
postulate can be phrased in a more
elegant mathematical way and that's what
we're going to do right we going to
phrase the postulate in a more elegant
way once you introduce special
relativity and you combine it with
quantum mechanics it's not a new
postulate it's um it's a consequence of
uh of special
relativity uh which was DX
Discovery okay instead of talking about
one particle let's talk about two
particles well let's let's go back to
classical statistical Mechanics for a
minute
In classical statistical
mechanics or classical mechanics of um
of a system of
particles if all the particles are the
same kind of
particle the question is do you treat
them as identical particles in this
following sense in counting the number
of configurations for
example uh we put particles into
boxes the boxes could be little boxes in
Phase space or it could just be
boxes four boxes we can put particles
into let's say we have two particles and
they're both the same kind of
particle right so here's here's a
configuration we can put two two of them
both into the same box that's clearly a
unique uh a unique
configuration or I can put one particle
in one box and the other particle in the
other box is that one configuration or
is it two
configurations uh if these particles
have names Harry and uh and uh Sally
Harry and Sally yeah if they have names
then you could put Harry here Sally here
or you could put Harry here and Sally
here and there seem to be two different
configurations uh in counting
configurations and calculating enpy and
so forth this could be the this sounds
like it's a difference now whether it is
an important difference or not as a
separate issue but do you count these as
separate uh
configurations you could always imagine
that these particles which
are identical to
you have a little tiny little bit of
paint on them that paints their name on
them but it's such a weak little bit of
paint classical paint not quantized
paint classical paint it's so so faint
so terribly faint that no experiment
that you ever could do could uh could
detect the name imprinted on the
particle but you would have to say they
were different particles Harry here and
Sally there would be different than
Sally here and and Harry there um or you
can say no I'm going to do statistical
mechanics as if these were the same
configuration
not think of the particles as
labeled now in fact you get the same
answers doesn't make any difference for
the classical statistical mechanics but
it's a conceptual difference putting a
particle here and a particle here is it
or is it not the same as switching them
if they're the same kind of
particle so that's a classical version
of the notion of identical particles and
In classical statistical mechanics we
usually assume that these SE are the
same configurations Harry Sally Sally
Harry they're the same configurations
and that's the way we do our counting
how many configurations are there for a
large number of particles well typically
you get some INF factorial different
ways of uh of relabeling the particles
and that goes into statistical mechanics
if you taken statistical mechanics
course you know that in Partition
functions there are these one over n
factorials in them and it's simply
keeping track or of the fact that if you
interchange two particles it's the same
configuration that's an assumption you
make in quantum mechanics you don't have
the luxury of doing one or the other it
is very definitely that particles are
identical in the sense that they do not
carry labels two electrons one electron
here and the other electron here is
mathematically identical and you
couldn't do it
otherwise
uh exchanging the
electrons same would true with photons
now having a photon here and an electron
here is not the same as having an
electron here and a photon here that's
clear that's that should be obvious they
have very different properties and you
can tell those two configurations apart
but interchanging and swapping around
which electron is which that's a
non transformation
on the state of a system and it also is
true of
photons so let's think about that and
what it tells us about the quantum
state of a pair of identical particles
let's take a pair of identical particles
this could be two
electrons and for the moment let's
forget uh spin or anything else we just
have two
electrons in uh in some
states let's forget spin
how do we describe two particles one
particle is described by a wave function
s of X where X is the position of the
electron what about two
electrons and in fact let's let's go
back a step what is the S of X what is
its meaning it's the overlap or the
inner product of an electron at x with
the state of the system s if s is the
state Vector of the
electron then it's ection or its inner
product onto a state localized at X is
called s of
X Suppose there were two electrons how
do you characterize the states of two
electrons well you characterize them by
two positions position of one and
position of the other let's call them X1
and
X2 that does not stand for different
directions of space now stands for the
two
electrons X1 and X2 and the wave
function is a function of two
coordinates instead of one s of X1 and
X2 that's the wave function of a two-
particle system it's a function of and
if you want the probability the
probability is a probability to find
particle one at position X1 particle 2
at position X2 so we have functions of
two variables when we have two
particles now let's let's think of the
operation of swapping the two
particles taking particle one and
replacing it by particle two and
particle two by particle one well that's
a
transformation that's a transformation
that generally will change S of X1 and
X2 it'll change it from s of x1x2 to
what
I of X2 and
X1 which is not the same thing in
general a function of two variables does
not have to be symmetric it does not
have to be such that if you interchange
the two arguments you get the same uh
you get the same function back so in
general a transformation it's a
transformation which swaps the two
particles let's call that transformation
let's give it a
name it's an operator it operates on a
wave function and gives a new wave
function so let's let's name
it let's call it the swap
operation let's call it
s and here's what s
does s acts on a
state with particle one at position X1
and particle 2 at position X2 how do I
know which which is particle one
particle one comes first particle 2
comes
second what does the swamp operation do
when it acts on a particle at position
one and a second particle at position
two it just swaps
them it gives you particle two sorry
particle one at position X2 and particle
2 at position X1 it just swaps them if
the particle had little names attached
to them this would mean
something here you would have Harry at
position one and Sally at position two
here you would have Sally at position
two and Harry at I'm not sure I said it
right but you know what I
mean you change them you just do a
little dance and uh and uh switch
them so this is a possible operation
that you can do on the state of two
particles
here's an interesting
fact take the operation s squared what
does s squ do it swaps and then it swaps
again it swaps and it swaps again what
happens if you swap
twice you get you get back the same
thing obviously you get back the same
thing even if the particles have little
names attached to them if you in
interchange Harry and Sally and then
interchange Harry and Sally again you
get back to the original uh
naming so what do we know about s squar
s squ must be
one as an operator s squ must be
one it's a unitary operator why should
it be a unitary operator because all
transformations on the space of states
are unitary so here's what we know about
s s is unitary
that means it doesn't change
probabilities it doesn't change
um uh inner products and S2 is equal to
1 what are the igen
values
of a matrix or an operator whose square
is one
either one or minus
one the only possibility S2 is equal to
1 means that the igen values are + one
or minus
one okay let's
let's make a new principle the new
principle is that
electrons or that identical particles
they could be photons they could be
electrons whatever
that for a specific kind of particle the
wave function when you when you
interchange two particles always comes
back to the same wave function that's if
s is equal to
1 or comes back to its negative if s is
equal to
minus1 see what that means let's take
the case + one
I think I'm beginning to fade I think
it's time to quit I think uh you're
probably also beginning to fade we we'll
go through firmians and bosons next time
but the basic idea is classifying the
wave functions of particles in terms of
what happens when you switch the
particles it's a basic quantum
mechanical process or qu basic quantum
mechanical operation the SW the swapping
of particles
and the notion of identical particles is
basically telling you that something
simple happens when you swap two
particles either the wave function does
this or it does that and we'll go we do
it next
week for more please visit us at
stanford.edu